Martin Vinæs Larsen	· Cand.scient.pol, Ph.d.
---------------------	--------------------------

May 4, 2018

CONTACT Department of Political Science,

Phone: (+45) 60 71 65 45 Aarhus University, Work e-mail: mvl@ps.au.dk Bartholins Allé 7. Private e-mail: vinaes@gmail.com DK-8000 Aarhus C, Denmark Web: MartinVinaes.github.io

RESEARCH **INTERESTS** Electoral accountability and the quality of electoral decision-making, economic voting, rational choice theory, political psychology, the role of information in EU elections and causal inference.

ACADEMIC **POSITIONS**

Department of Political Science, Aarhus University:

Jan. 2018 —

· Assistant professor

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen: Sep. 2017 — Dec. 2017

· Research Assistant

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen: Sep. 2013 — Aug. 2017

· Ph.D. Fellow

EDUCATION

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen:

Dec. 2017

- · Thesis: "Power Reveals: How Clarity of Responsibility Shapes Patterns of Electoral Accountability."
- · Advisor: Professor Kasper Møller Hansen.
- · Committee: Professor Michael Lewis-Beck, Professor Gabriel Lenz, and Professor Peter Thisted Dinesen (chair).

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen:

Aug. 2015

- · M.Sc. Political science
- · Thesis: "Voters Infer Incumbent Quality from the State of the Economy."

Chair in Electoral democracy, University of Montreal:

Aug. 2014 - Jan. 2015

· Visiting researcher

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen:

Jan. 2012

· B.Sc. Political science

ADDITIONAL TRAINING

ICPSR, University of Michigan:

Aug. 2014

· Summer Program: Introduction to Game Theory, Rational Choice Theory

Experiments, University of Oxford:

July 2012

· Summer Program

Summer Institute in Political Psychology, Stanford University:,

Aug. 2011

· Summer Program

OTHER POSITIONS EUvox:

Mar. 2014

· Communications director for Danish part of the EUvox VAA

Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen:

· Teaching Assistant in Research Methods

ARTICLES WITH REVISE & RESUBMIT

26. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Asmus Leth Olsen (2018). Reducing Bias in Citizens' Perception of Crime Rates: Evidence From a Field Experiment on Burglary Prevalence. *Revise & Resubmit to the Journal of Politics*.

Aug. 2010 — Jan. 2013

- 25. Larsen, Martin Vinæs; Frederik Hjorth; Kim Sønderskov; Peter Dinesen (2018). When Do Citizens Respond Politically to the Local Economy? Evidence from Registry Data on Local Housing Markets. *Revise & Resubmit to The American Political Science Review*.
- 24. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2018). Incumbent Tenure Crowds Out Economic Voting. *Revise & Resubmit to The British Journal of Political Science*.
- 23. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2018). Is the Relationship between Political Responsibility and Electoral Accountability Causal, Adaptive and Policy-specific? *Revise & Resubmit to Political Behavior*.
- 22. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Pedersen, Rasmus Tue (2018). Putting a Number on Preferences: How Enumerated Attitudes are Shaped by Ideology and Equivalency Framing. *Revise & Resubmit to The International Journal of Public Opinion Research*.

PEER REVIEWED ARTICLES

- 21. Beach, Derek; Hansen, Kasper M.; Larsen, Martin Vinæs (2017). How Campaigns Enhance European Issues Voting during European Parliament elections. *Political Science Research and Methods*, Early View.
- 20. Dahlgaard, Jens Olav; Hansen, Jonas H; Hansen, Kasper M; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2017) How Election Polls Shape Voting Behavior *Scandinavian Political Studies*, 40(3), 330 343.
- 19. Dahlgaard, Jens Olav; Hansen, Jonas H; Hansen, Kasper M; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2016). How are Voters Influenced by Opinion Polls? The Effect of Polls on Voting Behavior and Party Sympathy *World Political Science Review.* 12 (2), 283 300.
- 18. Esben Høgh; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2016). Can information increase turnout in European Parliament elections? Evidence from a quasi-experiment in Denmark. *JCMS: Journal of Common Market Studies*. 54 (6), 1495—1508.
- 17. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2016). Economic Conditions Affect Support for Prime Minister Parties in Scandinavia. *Scandinavian Political Studies*. 39 (3), 226—241.
- 16. Mats Joe Bordacconi; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2014). Regression to causality: Regression-style presentation influences causal attribution. *Research and Politics*. 1 (2).
- 15. Nielsen, Sigge Winther; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2014). Party Brands and Voting. *Electoral Studies*. 33, 153—165.

CONFERENCE AND WORKING PAPERS

- 14. Larsen, Martin Vinæs; Olsen, Asmus Leth (2017). Clarity of Responsibility and Incumbent Behavior. American Political Science Association Meeting, 2016, Panel: Political Economy of Advanced Industrial Democracies.
- 13. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2015). Is there a self-serving bias in attribution of political responsibility? *Presented at the Midwest Political Science Association Meeting*, 2016, *Panel: "Accountability for Economic Performance"*.

Danish Peer Reviewed Articles

- Dahlgaard, Jens Olav; Hansen, Jonas H; Hansen, Kasper M; Larsen, Martin Vinæs (2015). Hvordan påvirkes vælgerne af meningsmålinger? Effekten af meningsmålinger på danskernes stemmeadfærd og sympati for partierne. *Politica* 46 (1): 5—23
- 11. Nielsen, Sigge Winther; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Egeberg, Jesper de Hemmer (2011). Vi er alle spindoktorer. *Økonomi og Politik* 84 (1): 19—33

BOOK CHAPTERS

- 10. Dahlgaard, Jens Olav; Hjorth, Frederik; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Olsen, Asmus (2017). Meningsmålinger under valgkampen, in Hansen, Kasper Møller; Stubager, Rune: *Oprør fra udkanten*. Købehavn: Jurist- og Økonomforbundets Forlag.
- 9. Bisgaard, Martin; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2017). Den økonomiske situation og det politiske ansvar, in Hansen, Kasper Møller; Stubager, Rune: *Oprør fra udkanten*. Købehavn: Jurist- og Økonomforbundets Forlag.
- 8. Elmelund-Præstekær, Christian; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2017). Vælgeradfærd i de danske kommuner, in Elklit, Jørgen; Elmelund-Præstekær, Christian; Kjær, Ulrik: *KV13: Analyser af kommunalvalget 2013*. Odense: Syddansk Universitetsforlag.
- 7. Elmelund-Præstekær, Christian; Hansen, Kasper Møller; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2017). Den nationale valgvind blæser ikke med samme styrke for alle partier, in Elklit, Jørgen; Elmelund-Præstekær, Christian; Kjær, Ulrik: *KV13: Analyser af kommunalvalget 2013*. Odense: Syddansk Universitetsforlag.
- 6. Larsen, Martin Vinæs; Olsen, Asmus (2017). Hvem kan forudsige, hvem der bliver borgmester? Modellernes dumhed, massens klogskab?, in Elklit, Jørgen; Elmelund-Præstekær, Christian; Kjær, Ulrik: KV13: Analyser af kommunalvalget 2013. Odense: Syddansk Universitetsforlag.
- 5. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Nielsen, Sigge Winther (2016). Den kommenterede valgkamp, in Goul Andersen, Jørgen; Shamshiri, Ditte: *Vælgere på Vandring*. Frederiksberg: Frydenlund Academic.
- 4. Nielsen, Sigge Winther; **Larsen, Martin Vinæs**; Egeberg, Jesper de Hemmer (2012). Den politiske mandagstræner, in Nielsen, Sigge Winther: Politisk Marketing. København: Karnov Group.
- 3. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2012). Praktikerne har ordet: Samtaler med de danske partier, in Nielsen, Sigge Winther: Politisk Marketing. København: Karnov Group.

REPORTS

- 2. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs** (2014). Gennemsnit af meningsmålinger forudsiger valgresultatet. CVAP Working Paper Series 3/2016.
- Dahlgaard, Jens Olav; Hansen, Jonas H.; Hansen, Kasper M.; Larsen, Martin Vinæs (2014). Hvordan påvirkes vælgerne af meningsmålinger? Rapport om effekten af meningsmålinger på danskernes stemmeadfærd og sympati for partierne. CVAP Working Paper Series 1/2014.

WORK IN PROGRESS

- "Myopia and Economic Recessions" (with Gabriel Lenz)
- "Instability in Voting Models" (with Michael Lewis Beck & Richard Nadeau)
- "Raising Awareness without Raising Fears" (with Asmus Leth Olsen)
- "The Causal Effect of Political Fragmentation" (with Jacob Nyrup)

ACADEMIC TEACHING

Teaching:

M.Sc.-level courses:

- "Political Behavior: Classic theories and New approaches"
 - · Course design and course teaching: spring 2015.
- "Advanced Quantitave methods"
 - · Course design and course teaching: spring 2015.

BA.-level courses:

- "BSc thesis seminar"
 - · Ran workshops in spring of 2017.
- "Theories and Approaches to Political Science"
 - · Full course teaching spring 2014, lectures in fall 2014, 2015, 2016.
- "Advanced Quantitave methods"
 - · Course design and course teaching in spring 2015.
- "Research methods 2"
 - · Ran workshops in spring of 2014.
- "Research methods 1"
 - · Full course teaching in fall of 2010, 2011, 2012 and 2013.
- Academic supervision
 - · I have supervised 6 MSc thesis (9 students).

AWARDS

- Best Paper in Politica 2015.
- Nominated for Teacher of the Year 2012 and Teacher of the Year 2015 at the Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen for courses Research Methods 1 and Political Behavior: Classic Theories and New Approaches.

RESEARCH AND TRAVEL GRANTS

Research:

- "Raising Awareness without Raising Fears". Co-investigator with Asmus Leth Olsen (PI): Funding from *Trygfonden*. 986,398 DKK.
- "Too many chefs? Identifying the causal effect on political fragmentation on legislative effectiveness". Funding from *Aarhus University Research Foundation*. 40,000 DKK.

Travel grants:

- Oticon foundation: 25,000 DKK, 2015, 2016, 2017.

- Knud Højgaards foundation: 22,000 DKK, 2014, 2015.

- Augustinus foundation: 20,000 DKK, 2014.

- Danish Tennis Foundation: 10,000 DKK, 2014.

TALKS AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Paper presentations at conferences: American Political Science Association Conference 2015, 2016; Midwest Political Science Association 2015, 2016 (2); Amsterdam Political Psychology Conference 2015; Danish Political Science Association 2015, 2016 (2).

Clarity of Responsibility and economic voting. Presentation at Department of Political science, University Laval, Canada. 2014-11-27

Economic voting and time in office. Presentation at the Chair in Electoral Studies, University of Montreal, Canada. 2014-12-02

SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION AND ADMINISTRATION

Reviewer experience: Journal of Politics, European Journal of Political Research, Electoral Studies, Scandinavian Political Studies, European Union Politics, Political Behavior.

Discussant: Danish Political Science Association: 2015, 2016.

Chair: Danish Political Science Association: 2015.

Ph.D. representative, Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen, 2014 – 2016

Ph.D. club president, Department of Political Science, University of Copenhagen, 2016 – 2017

MEDIA

Regular commentator on political events, various news platforms: radio, TV, regional and national Danish newspapers (> 100 times a year since 2013).

Research results featured in:

- · P1 Orientering
- · Ugebrevet A4
- $\cdot \ Videnskab.dk$
- $\cdot \ Berlingske$
- $\cdot \ Politiken$
- · Information
- · Jyllands Posten
- · DR2 Deadline

POLITICAL WRITING

PoliLab, Politiken:

Sep. 2015 – Jun. 2016

· Contributer to PoliLab with articles about politics and political research.

Analysis, tv2.dk:

May 2014 - Jun. 2015

· Contributor to tv2.dk with articles about politics and political research.